<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Team | Dominick J. DeStasio]]></title>
  <link href="http://djdestasio.github.com/blog/categories/team/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://djdestasio.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-02-25T23:05:33-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://djdestasio.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Dominick J. DeStasio]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Sometimes It's Good to Be Skeptical]]></title>
    <link href="http://djdestasio.github.com/blog/2013/02/20/sometimes-its-good-to-be-skeptical/"/>
    <updated>2013-02-20T23:29:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://djdestasio.github.com/blog/2013/02/20/sometimes-its-good-to-be-skeptical</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A few days ago, I was involved in a meeting with several co-workers &mdash; including a few from the management team. The exact
subject matter of the conversation is mostly irrelevant except for the fact that a large portion of the conversation was
centered around values and principles that we all truly believe are important to what we do.</p>

<p>I almost always find conversations like the one that took place to be fascinating, because I think it&rsquo;s important to
understand the perspective of those around you. While it can be uncomfortable at times, often the conversations that can
have the biggest impact are the ones where the person on the other side of the table sees things differently than than the
rest &mdash; or at least owns up to that fact.</p>

<p>Regarding the values and principles that were being discussed, I have little doubt that if each person that was involved
in the conversation was asked how we &mdash; as a group &mdash; perform, there would be a degree of variance in the answers. The
hard part though, is getting that to come out in an open and honest setting. Some people will not come out and say how
they really feel because they do not want to be the ones with the spotlight, others might think that no matter what their
opinion is it won&rsquo;t change anything, and let&rsquo;s be honest&hellip;some people are just along for the ride.</p>

<p>Luckily (in my opinion), in this particular circumstance, there were a few people that spoke up and challenged the status
quo. When this kind of stuff happens, it&rsquo;s easy to look at those people and think that they just don&rsquo;t get it or that they
must not really be on board with what you&rsquo;re trying to accomplish &mdash; how could they see things so differently??</p>

<p>I am a huge believer in the strength of a team, largely because of the different talents and perspectives that each team
member brings to the table &mdash; which is why I believe it was good that someone wasn&rsquo;t afraid to bring up the fact that they
see things differently. Sometimes it&rsquo;s good to be skeptical. Not only is it good, but it&rsquo;s necessary for the growth of
individuals and organizations. Rather than rationalizing why someone on your team doesn&rsquo;t see the truth the way that you do,
it&rsquo;s far more beneficial challenge your own perspective and find out how to improve as a team.</p>

<p>I work with a great team of people and it is far more reassuring to me that those people are willing to challenge what we do on
a regular basis than it would be for everyone to be silent as if everything was perfect. No matter how good we are nothing
will ever be perfect and there will always be room for improvement as long as people are skeptical about the status quo to
drive things in a positive direction.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
